so I wonder if we can discuss today what
is
feeling and how is feeling different
from emotion
and also from
Sensation because these three are
commonly mixed up or regarded as the
same thing whereas actually um they're
quite different so I thought it would be
good to clear it
up so what is
feeling and how is that different from
let's say emotions
let's start with sensation because
that's the most
uh obvious difference I guess uhuh any
uhuh any
ideas sensation could be like any
sensation like sensation of cold
sensation of heat sensation of yeah
whatever and feeling maybe like
something more Primal more in the
background like General unpleasantness
and general like agreeable or neither of
them distinction so so are sensation
distinction so so are sensation
suffering can can Sensations Make You
Suffer Well if I cling to them like in
the sense that I believe that my
unpleasantness come from that
yes but so really not the sensation
Makes You Suffer it's the feeling
accompanying The Sensation that will
make you suffer
yeah so that right there is already a
primal distinction that would be
overlooked in many contemporary
practices and Views like cuz you you
would people would practice in the sense
of enduring their Sensations it's quite
a common thing uh while you're medit
ating and stuff like you have a pain in
your knee and you think that your
reactions to that you confuse that with
the same level as the duka that that
Buddha was talking about so by training
yourself to put up with Sensations you
think you're training yourself to put up
with your feelings but I mean you might
by coincidence s sort of be enduring
feelings at the same time but the fact
that you don't even see the distinction
means like you you're not actually
training the same thing CU you can't
train this is understanding by accident
so if you're having a unpleasant
sensation of your knee hurts or
something well I mean technically you
can't even say unpleasant sensation
that's like a like
aoron that that's a it's it's a you
could say a a sensation of of heat a
sensation of pain a sensation of cold
but you can't say unpleasant sensation
because that's already you're involving
the feeling there so you
you you can have um so unpleasant
sensation is already two things it's
it's perception which is the sensation
and feeling and furthermore even even
strictly speaking the notion of
sensation is also already somewhat of a
confusion yeah so you can distinguish in
terms of uh like obviously the way it
would be assumed would be more than it
really is really a sensation is just the
perception of touch it's one of the five
senses basically the fifth sense has the
counterpart of touches in the same way
that the eye has the counterpart of
sights so that's what a quote unquote
sensation is it's just a touch um I mean
that's what it should be and that's how
the suas describe it basically people
might kind of put more into it yeah
because then you see then it might still
be a further confusion about that so if
you use the word sensation in that sense
it it can be used in in the context of
dharm but if a scientist is going to
measure impulses going up and down your
nervous system or stuff that's happening
in your brain calling that sensation
creates more confusion because it is
conflating what is publicly observable
from a scientific point of view right
impulses traveling up and down your
nervous system with actual things like
heat and cold that are experiential and
fully outside of the scope of the
Sciences so the notion of sensation
itself as has already been established
by the existential phenomenologists is
sort of a hybrid notion that tends to
blur what is first person experiential
with what is third
person um non-experiential let's put it
like that so that's one confusion so we
should clear that up by saying that
sensation the way we are going to
discuss it is on the level of perception
which is fully Within in DH so we don't
need to discuss what's happening inside
the brain or the nervous system because
that's totally Irrelevant for practicing
Buddhist teaching and then that notion
of sensation specified should be further
distinguished from
feeling right yeah cuz that that
sensation um yeah like you said it
because of putting science but it
doesn't really belong really not not
that it's wrong in itself but putting it
where it doesn't belong then you would
make more out of this thing which is
absolutely not special in any any sense
like sights sounds smells taste touches
thoughts and then in regard to this you
have feeling none of those six things
are particularly kind of more special
than the other all of them are just
perception so but yeah if you start
assuming that kind of the sensation
going to your brain and stuff then and
then furthermore you're assuming that
freedom from suffering would be
something that you can measure based on
the whatever chemicals or reactions in
the brain well all what you're measuring
is basically um form you can't measure
feeling perception intention and cons
Consciousness the other Aggregates on
the basis of that so
um so yeah feeling is always something
that's uh personal it's always something
that is basically from that first person
point of view so the part that a
scientist might be able to observe would
be um maybe the heat C like if there are
some kind of nervous impulses that that
represent those Sensations those touches
then yeah that could be measured but
your personal relationship with that
that could the level where really the
development of Mind happens that you
wouldn't be able to measure that and
even then you could say a scientist
might measure that's something is 20° C
but whether that is for you warm or cold
is still another matter
yeah and it's um I mean the Su talk
about how for example um like the mind
of anun uh he would say like nobody
would be able to tell tell it apart
nobody would be able to to determine
where he stands basically so I mean with
a sensation kind of if if it were on
that level then you just measure this
thing and you can tell who's in our hand
based on this yeah very trivial kind of
uh mundane thing so and furthermore like
if your body just what happens if your
body if those chemicals and stuff stop
stop working the way they did which lead
you to what you think is freedom from
suffering then our hun would be kind of
reversible it would be impermanent
dependent dependent yeah dependent on
form literally dependent on form yeah so
how can how can that be what the Buddha
was actually teaching it's impossible
so um feelings how how to know what
you're feeling and how to tell it apart
from perception well just imagine um any
time in your life where if you let's say
you had a reward coming on account of
putting up with an unpleasant physical
sensation and like you were really close
to getting that
reward um I don't know
I mean even doing sports and stuff like
it's it's physically unpleasant but the
mental pleasure is there on the level of
feeling because you expect to win the
competition U you know all the the
praise and honor that's going to come
out of you winning this so there is a
pleasant feeling there even though the
sensation might be very
unpleasant in the on a physical level so
that is is the prime example of that
distinction between um feelings and
Sensations and then all the delight and
lust that the Buddha talked about is
towards your feelings so if a
sensation is not well theight and lust
in aversion for that matter um if a
sensation is not producing a feeling
let's say a pleasant sensation is not
producing a feeling a corresponding
feeling in regard to it then there can
be no Delight in that sensation like you
can be eating you know the best food in
the world for example but you're in a
really bad mood like something bad
really happened just happened to you you
won't be able to Delight in it because
the feeling that that is um reigning
over your experience is unpleasant so
that it's that's not compatible if it's
a really unpleasant situation even
though the sensation quote unquote the
The Taste is Pleasant you won't be able
to Delight in it so yeah so we could say
that there's feeling present for let's
say each and every sense base but
there's always one dominant or
overarching feeling which is either
Pleasant or unpleasant but other sense
bases could could differ yeah so
practically speaking it's probably most
useful to just ask the question what is
the overall feeling that is enduring
right now for my experience as a whole
and not start getting lost in particular
sense basis but just recognize that that
there will always be an overall feeling
that you find yourself within so to
speak yeah the Buddha said um on an
occasion where you're feeling pleasure
you you cannot be feeling pain at the
same time on the level of feeling
sensation like particular stuff can be
can be coming and going but on that
General level you always only have one
he said that in majima 74 I think he
said uh on an occasion where somebody
feels a pleasant feeling he doesn't feel
an unpleasant or either Pleasant or
unpleasant feeling because it is
exclusive like it
is in a on a practical sense you can
realize you can't be doing well and
doing bad at the same time it has to be
one of the two so that that kind of
um summarizes like what What a Feeling
is is kind of what is the answer to the
question how am I doing right now mhm
sorry it's not like the uh I mean you
can kind
of look at that and read it and say well
I don't know for instance right now like
I don't know my body is warm which is
pleasant but my knee hurts which is
unpleasant so therefore that's not true
but like it's on that more General mood
level yeah yeah so like how am I in the
most General sense how am I doing means
like um would I like this to
um would I like this to
continue or would I like it to change
and if the answer is I would like it to
change then you can know there is some
degree of unpleasantness there so
pleasure you would know pleasure is is
what you want more of this pleasure is
what you want less of and then there's
the third one which is the neither
Pleasant nor unpleasant feeling which is
essentially the one that you wouldn't
even even be able to recognize unless
you have been dwelling in seclusion
because the neither Pleasant or unpleasant
the neither Pleasant or unpleasant
Feeling by someone who's not restrained
is essentially automatically covered up
with either pleasure or pain because MH
it's so kind of
um slippery mhm it's like it it it's
it's below the threshold of the things
that you're used to to looking at so
then when it's there it
automatically you just can't stand it
and you turn it into something else you
get busy you get distracted you get that
you start thinking about stuff you can't
just stay with it quote unquote so yeah
I think it's as when it's not known it's
experienced as unpleasant but when that
feeling is known it actually experien as
pleasant yeah because it's the the lack
of disturbance that um for ordinary
person that's used to pleasure of the
wrong kind uh that lack of disturbance
really is is experienced more as a kind
of like um boredom like um kind of
anxiety yeah anxiety uneasiness sinking
which which is unpleasant yeah cuz you
it's like um like you've been
running with a certain momentum and then
suddenly like it stops but you still
need to kind of keep going and then you
overlook the fact that wait when I
actually stop running as I've been doing
before it it it is actually more
peaceful but because
the momentum kind of is the the thing
that you put first you don't see that
actually this is this is better so
neither Pleasant nor unpleasant feeling
is
um what a person then needs to start to
discern like Pleasure and Pain is is
essentially um anybody can tell if they
which is some basic instruction when
they're feeling Pleasant where than
feeling unpleasant but that neutral one
is
um so
then U since we cleared up what is the
U since we cleared up what is the
difference between feeling and and the
sensations then what would be
emotions yeah perhaps you can ask um
like are you responsible for your
emotions or are they things that happen
to you what would people here
say well I guess if I was responsible
will be always joyful always happy
always like kind of if I was controlling
like the whole processes of it I would
never experience anger or things like
that I guess
so say like I'm at least not fully
responsible for them to
appear anyone else any
ideas because it's a common view that
emotions are something that happen you
know I'm struck by jealousy or something
like this com
expression but I think that it is worth
well discussing right so emotion literally
discussing right so emotion literally
the word right emotion means the mind
being moved by things or disturbed
that's what that's what emotion
means and so it seems to me that it is
crucial to
recognize that all emotions are
intentional in the sense that they're
always about something but that
intentionality should be strictly
separated from the cause of your
emotions so for example someone breaks
my favorite coffee cup and I'm angry
with that person for having broken my
coffee cup that's what the emotion of
anger is about that's the
intentionality but that doesn't mean
that U my coffee cup having been broken
is the cause of my being
angry those are two totally separate
things so what is then the cause of me
getting angry when someone breaks my
favorite coffee cup why would that
happen well resistance to unpleasant
feeling yeah exactly what yeah very good
and then so on the level of emotions
then like what needs to be there in
order for that emotion to flood up to
begin with so okay maybe one step back so
with so okay maybe one step back so
there is an emotion like anger which is
unpleasant so that is how we can already
separate emotion from feeling so all
emotions are already let's say complete
um phenomenon well that's actually what
phenomena means it means like the the
totality of something which is present
and one aspect of it is that it is
either Pleasant unpleasant or nether
that's how we can separate Feeling Again
from emotion but now we can ask also the
question why is based on what is one
liable to emotions which are always
unpleasant by the way well that is also
what we can discuss but I just said it
like emotions are always unpleasant but
why do they happen
happen
attachment yeah exactly if if if I'm
attached to my favorite coffee cup then
somebody breaking it will make me angry
with that person for having broken my
coffee cup but if I confuse the
intentionality that my anger is about my
coffee cup having been broken with the
cause namely my attachment if that's if
that's conflated I will never be able to
free myself from emotions because stuff
in the world just happens you cannot
prevent that so if I do not want to be
liable to suffer the unpleasantness of
emotions rather than assuming full
control over the world which is
impossible you should actually move the
opposite direction and start questioning
whether you're still attached to things
so what is the um cuz then if you say
it's because you're attached to the
coffee cup then it might seem like so I
need to find everything that every
single thing that I'm attached to and
then give it up so how could you where
are you more acutely attached
to the Assumption of feeling that's
that's the most General well of course
so really you're attached to not
experiencing this pleasure so so you
might say the coffee cup if because many
times when people say like
um uh I shouldn't be attached to this
what they think of it as is more like I
shouldn't for example feel this pleasure
when the coffee cup is broken but that's
not on you like um you feel this
pleasure because that is part of the
Aggregates like it it is even if it's
not the coffee cup even if you give
everything up you live on the bridge and
you have no possessions quote unquote
when this body bro breaks you're going
to feel displeasure at least on that on
that account so the way to free yourself
fully is not to have attachment towards
what you feel in on that more more um
kind of Elemental level so you would um
fix every
Problem by
by giving up as you said the resistance
to unpleasant feeling like uh that is
the fundamental and that is the cause of
the emotion like if if there isn't any
um resistance to the unpleasant feeling
there cannot be anger there cannot be
jealousy there cannot be but the
unpleasant feeling is still there yeah
like because still I don't know you saw
something factually as I mean the Buddha
the Buddha gave the simly in I think
maaya 140 he said it's like if to
uh logs or pieces of wood were to be
rubbed together and then they produce
heat for as long as you're rubbing them
together they're going to be producing
heat in the same way Whenever there is a
a pressure or a contact that is to be
experienced as pleasant pleasant feeling
will remain yes for as long as and so
you have no control over what
situation is leading to an unpleasant
feeling that will depend on very factors
that are not in your control like you
might have been born with preference for
a certain food for example that another
person hates MH and then for as long as
you're in contact with this you will be
experiencing pleasure whereas the other
person will not M and so your say or
your job is regardless of what feeling
comes you must be able not to lean
towards it or resist it and on that
level then
it doesn't matter like what specific
thing it is yeah that is generally for
basically all phenomena that have all
phenomena have feeling as a constituent
so this is the level where basically the
practice of Dharma applies and one um
let's say uh and so where it also
applies is with emotions which is just
one kind of phenomena that also happens
in people's life so anger if she said
Envy jealousy loneliness self-pity and
so on they're all unpleasant and so once
we have cleared up that distinction
between the intentional structure and
the cause of the emotion right being the
the resistance towards not wanting to
experience unpleasant feeling one
basically should go about it as we have
discussed in other talks already um so
then you see but the difficulty is then
that there can be natural tendency to
wanting to get rid of the emotions
because they are unpleasant so I
shouldn't feel angry um it's so childish
to feel jealous um and and all those
things whereas
actually yeah that phenomena called
emotion is still what happens but one
once to then realize that it does still
happen on account of not having
understood that feeling so I would say
then that one is 100% fully responsible
for whether one suffers on account of
emotions yeah so and that is a counter
Inu statement because people would
generally assume emotions are something
that happened to me but I but I'm still
inclined to say yeah but that's because
certain other things that those emotions
depend upon have not been abandoned and
so they fully come with in the range of
responsibility as well so there's a
there's a sort of a double kind of um
contrast happening there so on the one
hand they are you are fully responsible
but at the same time you don't have
control over them as you you said before
it's not like you decide to be angry no
uh for a pu that's how it works like for
a person who doesn't see the sign of
their mind means a person who doesn't
see how they resist or how they Delight
in their feelings means they don't see
as the Buddha would call it the fuel
that's powering these emotions so then
what with what they would be trying to
do as you said just now is like try to
get rid of the emotions directly by coun
ing them with this like when I have
anger I counter it with the emotion of
meta yeah but it's really the only way
to actually solve the issues that have
manag it is to see and recognize that
intention to either how the the mind is
either leaning towards or leaning away
from the feeling and then don't worry
about the emotion because you can't that
that is a reason on account of what you
did in the past and you can't like undo
that emotions you could say um when when the
emotions you could say um when when the
suas talk about the results of your
actions mhm sometimes obviously there is
a component of like you know you are
stingy and then as a Buddha would say in
the next life you would be reborn as a
poor person or whatever but more
importantly uh you could say emotions
are the results of your actions your
action in the sense of resisting feeling
so resisting feeling for example having
resisted feeling in the past the result
of that is is when you encounter
displeasure anger will be there that's a
result manifesting in this way yeah this
particular ways yeah that's that so
that's like a foundation of resistance
that then gets manifested in these so if
if it happens to be that something bad
or something annoying happens you're
going to get angry if you see uh I don't
know uh pleasure it what's going to
happen is you're going to be craving for
it if you see if you're sleep SLE that's
going to result in you getting lazy if
your mind gets um you know has a lot of
movement in it that's going to result in
restlessness so you see what I'm
describing now is basically emotions you
could take it kind of on the same level
as the five hres yes yes it comes up as
a result of things that you've been
doing in the past but when it's there
you can't just cover it up and get rid
of it you have to remove the cause and
uh the cause is the cause is right now
like the cause is that even now look I'm
trying to get rid of this emotion why
because I'm still resisting I'm still uh
maintaining the same principle of
resisting unpleasant feeling so then
like anything that you might do you
replace this with that and you antidote
with loving kindness and stuff all of
that is still within the fact that you
resist displeasure so you're feeding the
same thing even if you successfully
manage to to um you know get the emotion
that you want the fact is you're still
not actually addressing the the
fundamental cause so then in the future
when other unpleasant feelings manifest
you're going to have to go through the
same thing again emotion is going to be
there and you're going to have to
counter it with something else but if
you actually address the the craving for
or against feeling then emotions would
not arise in the first place so you
don't need to counter or manage or do
anything so that's kind of
the the yeah but you see that that's all
correct but would you not say like for
example if somebody still has to view
that anger might serve a use or purpose
that there are occasions where it is in
your welfare to be angry then will
somebody be able to contemplate the dama
correctly on the level of feeling if
they still hold a view like that so um
perhaps we should make a slight this is
all correct but I think to go one step
slightly back M then there is a whole
area there where there is a ton of
confusion where people might think no no
no if this that happens in my life
certainly I'm justifi and being angry
well those views need to go because to
the extent that you allow
room for anger being useful you will not
be able to rightly endure the displ of
the anger when it rises that that that
that anger won't won't go so one also
has View views about emotions and it
seems to me that it is quite useful to
come to regard them as generally quite
useless and as unpleasant as basically
seeing them as part of suffering um and
and that fundamentally they need not be
there yeah and but I think that might
also be confused because again if you
don't see that distinction between
displeasure um between emotion and
feeling it might sound like oh I
shouldn't have emotions anymore sounds
like you should become like some sort of
blob of nothing basically but no it's
um emotions are on top of like
gratuitously added on top of the
feelings so and feelings in and of
themselves when you feel something
unpleasant you
will without emotion be able to do
something to fix that situation if it is
something that's not un wholesome for
example so as a Buddha would say um when
his back would hurt he would lie down
when his uh when somebody would say
something really foolish like
misrepresenting him he would have the
capacity to tell them off and strongly
rebuke them without having emotions M so
emotion is the problem with emotion is
that it's something that kind of like
you're subjected to that's the main
characteristic of emotions like you're
not really in control of this so you
might be able to say like oh I
I need this so that I can do such and
such but really you're not using it it's
using you that's the whole thing so you
don't you you don't have like a you you
might believe that you're using your
anger for a beneficial but really if you
if you ask yourself I don't have a say
in this like if if I if I tell myself to
stop being angry you won't be able to to
do it by choice so it's really
controlling you uh so well to some
extent I guess it would depend on
some degree of Faith but at the same
time like
clarifying the actual meaning of these
terms because um see for example people
who who have who have the view that if
you can't see the distinction between
these three things and you think that
feelings are Sensations and then the
whole thing just gets messed up because
how can they how can then you understand
the statement that you get rid of the
emotions but you still have feelings mhm
to to then that would sound like oh I
just have Sensations and then um
mentally there is no Pleasure and Pain
and that's what people would think of as
a Naran is a kind of robots that that
only has Sensations and there is no
feeling so the whole thing gets get
would get scrambled up but when you see
the difference between these three
things you see there can still be
pleasure like a mental experience of
pleasure there can still be a mental exp
experience of displeasure
and those things are always as you said
intentional so there will always be uh
to put it corly like an object that this
thing is directed towards so you will be
able to make choices in regard to that
object so what then is the need for
emotion like if something needs to be
done you have all you need you have the
feeling and you have the intention so
the emotion is kind of a really might
seem like like um
kind of you might justify it after the
fact like because you can't get rid of
it then you convince yourself that that
uh you need to have it or something but
really if you're honest with
yourself if I had a choice not to have
this you would be that's the whole point
you would be much better off without
emotions but that doesn't mean that
there can't be any feeling because they
will be nor does it mean that there
can't be any Sensations either because
there will still be heat and cold and
well and and and all those things so
that's not the issue either mind you
some people might say like I'm sure some
people if you ask them you give them a a
a button or something that press this
and you won't have emotions anymore well
a good amount of people might be scared
of that because of their own Assumption
of um what their own existence is
basically like they would think not
having emotions is just going to be this
kind of torture Bleak kind of uh
lifeless uh States but really it is
where the like everything that you're
seeking in your life
by completely the wrong way really is
because you are essentially trying to
get rid of your emotions because you are
already moved in the first place by
things in the world and the question is
is it pleasurable to live with the mind
that is moved by random things happening
in the world yeah well obviously an
intelligent person would come to the
conclusion that it isn't yeah you could
say that this existence is depends on
movement so if you if uh people
basically see that emotions as a kind of
movement and depending on it so that's
become very core of existence being yeah so
very core of existence being yeah so
that's why it's so difficult to imagine
not have emotions because you go to the
extreme of basically imagining that this
is livess or you go to The Other Extreme
that's why the Buddha said there are
only two extremes that people with the
you can go either existence so like I
Delight in everything I I welcome my
emotions I act out of them and then
nonexistence no emotions no nothing just
black so you can't see the middle way
get rid of the emotions but all the
feelings are perfectly fine because that
was not even your your fault like the
feelings comes
that's just a constituent that's right
yeah so um so really with with this
emotion thing it's like a what you would
call a Stockholm syndrome like people
might might kind of you know be be
saying that they're happy with this
while they're being held hostage that's
it by their own emotions even that like
that kind of reaction to the idea of not
having emotions is an emotional reaction
that's your capter kind of convincing
you oh no it's bad outside don't go out
there yeah yeah so it's really like um
it's something that needs to be
contemplated to
see as The Bu said um it it takes
discernment to Value nibana like nibana
is is not regarded as as pleasant by
default because it's the sensation of
emotions it's the sociation of being and
as he said the majority of of people in
the world are dependent on being they
Delight in being I mean that's why he
didn't want to teach the dama in the
first place because he felt like nobody
would understand and you could put it
that way because most people would not
even be able to conceive of the fact
that not having emotions is good so then
you felt like well I'm going to talk to
this to these people and it's just going
to be result in frustration because like
it's going against the entire thing that
defines them so it's um
train training yourself to to see that
uh going against the grain is is
Pleasant or is certainly better than
would than would you have even if it's
not immediately even if there is some
immediately even if there is some
dissonance at the beginning you use your
discernment to see like well no it would
be better not to be controlled by this
MH I mean right now I am suffering on
account of this practice because I'm
being controlled by my emot like that's
why practice is difficult because the
emotions are still there
so have you cleared up sufficiently the
difference between emotion feeling and
sensation how do you feel about it e